# OBJECTIVE: Principal / Senior Developer / Technical Project Lead / Software Architect SKILLS:

30+ years of hands-on software development experience. 20+ years of Java. 10+ years of architecture. Design and programming. Service Oriented Architectures and microservices, REST and GraphQL. Distributed systems and high availability. Public API design and implementation. Database design, administration and programming. Cloud Computing, expert-level Amazon Web Services. IAAS and PAAS. Big Data, ML and recommendation systems. Workflow applications and rule engines. Application servers. Search-based application and solutions. Messaging, asynchronous processing, streaming and observability. Strong cryptography and network security.

Full, agile or traditional software development lifecycle. Building solid teams, mentoring and education of junior developers. Task estimates, project and budget planning, formal leadership and management.

#### **KEYWORDS:**

C, C++, Java, Oracle, Spring, GraphQL, Hibernate, MVC, JMS, JSP/JSTL, JDBC, stored procedures, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server, NoSQL, REST APIs, Hbase, MongoDB, Hadoop, Spark, Pig, Lucene, Solr, Elasticsearch, Tomcat, Apache, LXC containers, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS, S3, EC2, ELB, RDS, SQS, DynamoDB, Azure, Linux, Windows, Maven, Gradle, Junit, Jenkins, CI, nodejs, Typescript, serverless

#### **EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS:**

BS in Mathematics and Computer Science
1992-1994 Lawrence Technological University, Detroit, Michigan
BS in Applied Information Systems
1986-1991 Industrial University, Baku, Azerbaijan
Sun Certified Architect for J2EE platform
Sun Certified Programmer for Java 2 platform
Published industry author and patent holder
Naturalized US citizen, employment is fully authorized

### **EXPERIENCE:**

## 2021-present Independent Software Technologist, Richmond, VA

Successfully developed and sold bespoke software technology for small businesses. Solution areas included enterprise search and automated provisioning of secure networks.

2017-2021 Senior Software Development Engineer Amazon, Seattle, WA

Amazon Explore virtual presence, Luna game streaming, Prime Air drones, Kuiper satellites. Delivered diverse set of successful projects. Services, asynchronous workflows, e-commerce, large scale integration, game and interactive streaming, serverless, anomaly detection and

mediation, fleet management. Architecture and team leadership. Mentored and organized junior developers. Assisted business development with strategy and estimates.

Technology included but not limited to Java, nodejs, GraphQL, AWS services and tools.

2016-2017 Senior Principal Software Engineer Concur, Bellevue, WA

Led several initiatives converting large legacy applications to smaller, more manageable services. Integrated disperse distributed workflows. Designed and developed innovative loosely connected lightweight messaging framework aimed at rapid development of business logic decoupled from messaging substrates. Java, REST, Springboot, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS.

**2014-2016 Principal Software Engineer – Social Intelligence** *Salesforce.com, Seattle, WA* As part of Salesforce Chatter teams ("Facebook for business"), worked on discovery, recommendation and delivery of relevant content to users of leading enterprise social network and Salesforce Communities. Used traditional databases and Big Data tools to extract and process variety of signals from user's posts, likes, follows, comments etc. to identify and expose trending topics and other relevant information and provide recommendations. Promoted culture of unit testing and many other improvements of the development process.

2012-2014 Senior Program Manager Microsoft, Redmond, Washington
As part of Microsoft Autopilot, designed, evaluated and analyzed very large

As part of Microsoft Autopilot, designed, evaluated and analyzed very large-scale logging, tracing and monitoring systems in Bing and Windows Azure environments. Identified commonality between disperse systems and teams, facilitated emergence of common vision and strategy. Prepared design documents, developed and validated product features, managed commitments across multiple teams.

**2011-2012 Senior Software Engineer – Global Payments** *Expedia, Bellevue, Washington* Designed and implemented new features and improvements in Expedia's complex SOA environment including Web Services and various internal frameworks. Coordinated development activities with offshore teams, drove agile development processes and improved product release practices.

**2010-2011 Senior Software Engineer** *F5 Networks, Seattle, Washington* Contributed to multiple components of F5 Enterprise Manager product. Responsible for ondevice storage architecture including database-driven storage and free-form search. Implemented collection and processing of per-device performance management statistics, corresponding UI elements, bug fixes and overall improvements.

**2006-2010** Senior Software Development Engineer Amazon, Seattle, Washington Engaged in number of challenging projects working on Amazon-size solutions as part of Amazon Payments, Distributed Database Systems and Amazon Web Services teams. Was primary developer of three new Amazon Web Services, including Amazon Relational Database Service (RDS) and Amazon Elastic Beanstalk, from conception to public availability. Migrated core business components of Amazon retail website to SOA.

1991-2010 Multiple Software Engineering and Management Positions

Retail, Airspace, Defense, Government, Travel, Warehousing, Logistics and other industries